//define the questions and answers
const questions=[
{
question:"The first book of the bible is called?",
answers:['genesis','exodus','john','matthew'],
corrrectAnswer:0                          
},
{
question:"What are the first three word in the bible ?",
answers:['Jesus is lord ','God love us','in the beginning','Jehovah is God'],
corrrectAnswer:2                          
},
{
  question:"How many Days God Creation take place ?",
 answers:['6','5','7','2'],
 corrrectAnswer:0                         
 },
 {
question:"Who is the father of Abner?",
 answers:['David','Saul','Ner','Jesse'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                        
},
{
 question:"Which book has told us that God so loved the World ?",
answers:['matt','john','luke','psalm'],
corrrectAnswer:1                        
 } ,                                                        {
 question:"When isaac is dying which food he requested ?",
 answers:['goat meat','pepper soup','vernison','meat'],
corrrectAnswer:2                         
 },
 {
question:"Thou shall not steal is what commandment ?",
answers:['9th','10th','7th','8th'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                                                         {
  question:"in what country jesus talk to a woman beside a wall ?",
 answers:['Gadara','idumaea','judea','samaria'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
},
{
  question:"What colour did nahum say the soilders shield are ?",
 answers:['Gold','silver','red','black'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                         
 }, 
 {
 question:"What word did paul say that stirred his audiance to anger ?",
answers:['messiah','Gentile','jesus','Abraham'],
corrrectAnswer:1                        
},                      
{
 question:"Who met jesus in the country of the Gergesenes ?",
answers:['his disciples','A multitude','possessed man','a harlot'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                         
 },                       
 {
 question:"How many criminals was crucified with Jesus ?",
  answers:['6','3','7','2'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                     
 {
 question:"What type of wood did Noah use to build the ark?",
answers:['Gopher','plank','accacia','cedar'],
corrrectAnswer:0                         
 },
 {
 question:"Who wrestle an Angel?",
 answers:['Adam','jacob','Esau','moses'],
corrrectAnswer:1                         
 }, 
 {
 question:"Who accused jesus of an association with beehebub ?",
 answers:['levites','priests','pharisees','samaritans'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                         
 },
 {
  question:"What element form the status head in Nebuchadnezzar's dream ?",
 answers:['Iron','Bronze','Gold','clay'],
corrrectAnswer:2                        
 },                                            
 {
  question:"What is the number of jacob's wives excluding concubines?",
 answers:['1','4','7','2'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                      
 {
   question:"who raised Esther?",
  answers:['Nehemiah','Mordecai','jeremiah','Enoch'],
corrrectAnswer:1                         
},                      
{
  question:"After whom is the city of samaria named?",
 answers:['omri','Ahab','shemer','luti'],
corrrectAnswer:2                         
 },                      
 {
 question:"in the beginning was the world and the word was with God, and the word was_______?",
 answers:['Good','complete','holy','GOD'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                      
 {
 question:"From where did paul write his letter to the Ephesians ?",
answers:['temple','Athens','prison','timothy house'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                         
},                      
{
 question:"After the flood, what was the sign of convenant that GOD made with Noah and his Descendants ?",
 answers:['Dry land','A dove','fire','Rainbow'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                      
 {
  question:"Who came with paul and barnabas to jeruselem?",
 answers:['timothy','peter','titus','john'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                         
},                      
{
 question:"Paul teaches that in christ through  we can approach God with what?",
 answers:['confidence','gift','tithing','mourning'],
 corrrectAnswer:0                         
}, 
{
 question:" Who asked how can a man be born again?",
 answers:['peter','Nicodemus','thomas','philip'],
corrrectAnswer:1                        
 },                      
 {
 question:"What was the name of Naomi husband ?",
 answers:['Elimelech','Hebron','Ahab','Boaz'],
corrrectAnswer:0                         
},                      
{
question:"I am the____of sharon and the ____of the valley ?",
answers:['child,infant','husband,wife','king,queen','Rose,lily'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                      
 {
question:"What was Hezekiah's first order of business as king of judah ?",
answers:['consecrating the temple','building idols','killing of isreal','taking a wife'],
corrrectAnswer:0                         
},                      
{
question:"what was the name of the chief workman of the terbernacle ?",
 answers:['moses','Bezaleel','joshua','Dan'],
 corrrectAnswer:1                         
 },
 {
question:"What did jesus feed the 5000 with ?",
 answers:['wine & bread','rice & beans','lamb & herb','bread & fish'],
corrrectAnswer:3                         
}, 
{
 question:"In what book does the parting of the red sea take place ?",
 answers:['Exodus','Number','Genesis','john'],
corrrectAnswer:0                         
 },
 {
question:"When jesus enter the city of bethany he was hungry he saw a tree that didn't bear any fruit so he cursed it, what type of tree was it ?",
answers:['fig','Apple','orange','olive'],
 corrrectAnswer:0                         
 },
 {
 question:"What does the authur of Ecclesiastes consider more bitter than death ?",
answers:['A blessing & calamity ','an idolatarous woman','rebellious children','flesh & blood'],
corrrectAnswer:1                         
},                                                          {
  question:"what does the preacher of Ecclesiates compare the word of the wise to ?",
 answers:['Goads & nails','hammer & Anvils','precious jewels','flourishing garden'],
 corrrectAnswer:0                         
 },                                                         {
   question:"Who denied knowing jesus ?",
 answers:['peter','james','judas','john'],
 corrrectAnswer:0                         
}, 
{
question:"After jesus was baptised What form did the Holy spirit descend upon him in ?",
 answers:['pigeon','lion','lamb','dove'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
},                                                          {
 question:"What were the isrealites supposed to put arround the doors of their house to save themselves from the last plague in Egypt ?",
answers:['Holy water','honey','lambs blood','their blood'],
corrrectAnswer:2                         
 },                       
 {
 question:"Who said thou art the christ son of the living God  ?",
answers:['thomas','nathanael','peter','james'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                         
},                      
{
 question:"Where did jesus had a conversation with samaritan woman?",
answers:['church','synagogue','At well','Galilee'],
corrrectAnswer:2                        
},                      
{
 question:"According to paul, which is a sign of spiritual maturity ?",
answers:['following new teachings','blindness of heart','childlike innocence','speaking the truth in love'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                      
 {
 question:"The memory of the just is blessed, but the name of the wicked shall ______ ?",
 answers:['flourish','win','rot','bloom'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                        
 },                      
 {
 question:"To what disciple did jesus say blessed are those who not seen and yet have believed ?",
 answers:['peter','philip','Andrew','thomas'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                     
 {
question:"When Esther was taken to be prepared for the king what secret did mordecai tell her to keep ?",
 answers:['she was a jew','she was a slave','she was a thief','she is married before'],
 corrrectAnswer:0                         
},                      
{
question:"But whosoever  shall lose his life for my sake and the gospel, the______?",
 answers:['one will be king','one will not lose it','same shall save it','same shall die'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                         
},                     
{
 question:"In a failed healing attempt, what did Gehazi use to heal, an old woman's son ?",
 answers:['jordan river','stick','Elisha staff','Moses'],
 corrrectAnswer:2                         
  },                      
  {
 question:"Of what material were all solomon drinking vessels made ?",
 answers:['Bronze','Gold','diamond','silver'],
 corrrectAnswer:1                         
 },                      
 {
  question:"Mention of the number of beast 666 can be found where  ?",
answers:['john','act','isaiah','Revelation'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                      
 {
question:"Who was jehosheba ?",
 answers:['sister of a king','wife of a priest','daughter of king','all'],
corrrectAnswer:3                         
},                      
{
  question:"How many priest were playing the trumpet at the dedication of the temple ?",
 answers:['1200','120','300','100'],
 corrrectAnswer:1                        
 },                      
 {
 question:"The kingdom of God can be inherited by which of the followings ?",
 answers:['robbers','drunkards','unrighteous','none'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
 },                      
 {
question:"who had strength because of his long hair ?",
 answers:['samuel','elijah','gideon','samson'],
 corrrectAnswer:3                         
},                       
{
  question:"On his deathbed, who did jacob calls a fruitful bought ?",
   answers:['isaac','Asher','benjamin','Joseph'],
   corrrectAnswer:3 
},
{
  question:" What appeared just before elijah was taken up into heaven?",
   answers:['an oarless boat','A sack of Gold',' A chariot of fire',' A bronze ox'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
}, 
{
  question:" The dry bones raised to life appeared as what ?",
   answers:['Goliath','Israel Ancestors',' Ghost','  Avast army'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" paul says we should do what to those that persecute us?",
   answers:['Curse','Bless',' Forgive','  Preach'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:" in the book of micah, God said woe unto them that devise what ?",
   answers:['Hatred','Charity','Iniquity',' Murder'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:" Where was jesus when the desciples asked him about his return and the end all thing?",
   answers:['jerusalem','sea of Galilee',' Mount of olives',' Bethlehem'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
}, 
{
  question:" what part of the body is the light of the body ?",
   answers:['Ear','Eye',' Mouth','Hand'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
}, 
{
  question:" Who did paul send back to thessalonica to see what was happening there?",
   answers:['Timothy','silvanus',' silas','Gallio'],
   corrrectAnswer:0
},
{
  question:" What is the third miracle Moses show the pharaohs of Egypt?",
   answers:['All water turn blood','A plague of frogs',' A plague of lice ',' famine'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:" JESUS choose matthew as one of his disciples . what was matthew's occupation ?",
   answers:['Fisherman','Tent maker',' Tax collector','Capenter'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},                                                                 {
  question:" In which city did david reign over all judah and israel?",
   answers:['Bethlehem','Jerusalem',' Socoh',' Hebron'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
}, 
{
  question:" whose name means 'because' i asked him of the Lord?",
   answers:['Eli','Samuel',' Hannah','Elkanah'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},  
{
  question:" How many israelites did God use to win victory over Midianites?",
   answers:['21000','100000',' 8000',' 300'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" Christ is the LORd of what?",
   answers:['Livings','Deads',' living and the dead','None'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
}, 
{
  question:" The harvest is plentiful but_______?",
   answers:['many will be hungry','The famers are few',' the labourers are few',' the sheaves are few'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
}, 
{
  question:" with what did Elisha cursed Gehazi?",
   answers:['infidelity','Boils',' Leprosy','Hiv'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:" Who avenges the defilling od dinah by killing Hamor, Shechena and the men ?",
   answers:['Simeon and levi','Benjamin and joseph',' judah and dan',' jacob and Esau'],
   corrrectAnswer:0
},
{
  question:" Which river did not flow through the Garden of Eden ?",
   answers:['Gihon','tigris',' Euphrates',' Jordan'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" Whose heart did the LORD open in thyatira?",
   answers:['Lydia','Mary','Rachel',' sarah'],
   corrrectAnswer:0
}, 
{
  question:" Who did solomon petition for supplies and workers for the temple's construction ?",
   answers:['King of Trye','King of syria',' King of Hittite','King of judah'],
   corrrectAnswer:0
},
{
  question:"Faith without ______ is dead ?",
   answers:['water','food','work','time'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:"which runaway slave became pauls son while paul was in prison  ?",
   answers:['philemon','Timothy',' Barnabas','Onesimus'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" who was the son  Abraham had by his wife Sarah ?",
   answers:['Ishmael','jacob',' isaac','Esau'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:" Where did the LORD speak with Moses after they came out of Egypt ?",
   answers:['Mount Horeh','Wilderness of Sinai',' Mount Olives','Camp of Reuben'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:" Jesus said the Kingdom of God is like what seed ?",
   answers:['Mustard','Pomegranate',' Grape','Fig'],
   corrrectAnswer:0
},
{
  question:" Who was mary and marthas brother ?",
   answers:['James','Simon',' Aquila','Lazarus'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" what was with God and Manifested into us ?",
   answers:['Firmament','Knowledge','Eternal life',' Discernment'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:"Who is the Author of the Book of Songs of Song ?",
   answers:['Solomon','Paul',' David','Manna'],
   corrrectAnswer:0
},
{
  question:" Whom did Jesus say should bury the Dead ?",
   answers:['Family','The dead',' Friends','Priests'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:" who had a dream of a ladder that reached to heaven ?",
   answers:['Jacob','Abraham',' Daniel','Isaiah'],
   corrrectAnswer:0
},
{
  question:" Everyone that is proud in heart is what to the LORD ?",
   answers:['A delight','A servant',' an aborminatio','A son'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:" in what city did philip perform miracle ?",
   answers:['Jerusalem','Sidon',' Samaria','Egypt'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:" what was the land that GOD gave to Israelites ?",
   answers:['Edom','Moab',' Midian','Canaan'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" what was simon peter's occupation before he met Jesus  ?",
   answers:['Zealot','Tax collector',' tent maker','Fisher man'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:"what is the name of the well that Abraham and abimelech quarrel over ?",
   answers:['Param','Kedesh',' Shur','Beersheba'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:"which angel appeared most often in daniels vision ?",
   answers:['Thummim','Urim',' Gabriel','Michael'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:"paul says the end of the law of righteousness is what ?",
   answers:['God','Christ',' The Bible','Faith'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:"How many thieves were crucified alongside of jesus ?",
   answers:['3','1',' 2','4'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:" In Isaiah chapter 6, Who did Isaiah see ?",
   answers:['King of Israel','God',' his Father','His son'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:" But those things which proceed out of the _____come forth from the _____ ?",
   answers:['Heart,mouth','Mouth,mind','Mouth,Heart','mind,mouth'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:" who were the recipients of the epistle to the Roman ?",
   answers:['Caesar"s household','soilders who crucified jesus',' all the saints in rome','Catholic church'],
   corrrectAnswer:2
},
{
  question:"who warned paul of the plot against him ?",
   answers:['His sister','His nephew',' His brother','Festus'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:" How many days did God's creation take place ?",
   answers:['5','6',' 8','7'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:" In the new land the Israelites where no to do what with their formal enemies ?",
   answers:['Worship','dine with',' forgive','Marry'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" What kind of person , according to the preacher of Ecclesiastes, is no better than an unenchanted Serpent ?",
   answers:['A dreamer','a teller of secrets',' A coy woman','None of the above'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" Of what were the candlestickes of the Temple made ?",
   answers:['silver','brass','wood','Gold'],
   corrrectAnswer:3
},
{
  question:" How was paul sent to italy ?",
   answers:['By horseback','by sea',' By carriage','by foot'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:" what must GOD servant not do ?",
   answers:['drink wine','quarrel',' Eat meat','go to parties'],
   corrrectAnswer:1
},
{
  question:"what does paul call timothy in his opening salutation of his first letter to him ?",
   answers:['son in the faith','brother in christ','lover of GOD','My peaceful child'],
   corrrectAnswer:0
},
                                          
]
//initialize the game
let currentQuestion=0;
let score=0;

//display the first question
displayQuestion()
//function to display the current question

function displayQuestion(){
const questionDisplay=
document.getElementById("question-display");
questionDisplay.innerHTML=
questions[currentQuestion].question;

const answerOptions=
document.getElementById("answer-options");
answerOptions.innerHTML="";
for(let i=0;i<questions[currentQuestion].answers.length;i++){
const answerOption=
document.createElement("button");
answerOption.innerHTML=
questions[currentQuestion].answers[i];
answerOption.onclick=checkAnswer;
answerOptions.appendChild(answerOption);                         
}
}
//function to check the players answer
function checkAnswer(event){
const playerAnswer=event.target.innerHTML;
if(playerAnswer===questions[currentQuestion].answers[questions[currentQuestion].corrrectAnswer]){
 score ++;
 alert("correct👍");
}
else{
alert("incorrect.The correct answer is  "   +    questions[currentQuestion].answers[questions[currentQuestion].corrrectAnswer]);                          
}   
currentQuestion++;
if(currentQuestion>=questions.length){
 alert("Game over! Your final score is "  +        score);                         
} 
else{
 displayQuestion();                         
}                      
}
















